欢迎来到这门关于编译器的课程, 我的名字是Alex Aiken, 我是这里的教授
Welcome to this course on compilers. My name is Alex Aiken. I'm a professor here
在斯坦福大学, 我们将要讨论的是
at Stanford University. And we're going to be talking about the implementation of
编程语言有两种主要的实现方法
programming languages. >> There are two major approaches to implementing
编程语言、编译器和解释器。现在, 这门课主要是
programming languages, compilers, and interpreters. Now, this class is mostly
关于编译器, 但是, 我想说几句关于解释器的
about compilers. But, I do want to say a few words about interpreters here in the
第一讲, 解释器会做什么呢, 我要画一个
first lecture. So, what does an interpreter do? Well, I'm gonna draw a
在这里, 这个方框是解释器, 它需要, 我用一个大的标签来标记它
picture here, this box is the interpreter, and it takes, let me label it with a big
我, 它作为输入, 你的程序, 你写的, 不管你的数据是什么
I, it takes as input, your program. That you wrote, And, whatever data that you
想要运行程序, 它直接产生输出, 意思是
want to run the program on. And it produces the output directly. Meaning that
它在程序执行之前不会对程序进行任何处理
it doesn't do any processing of the program before it executes it on the
输入, 所以你只需要写程序, 然后在数据上调用解释器,
input, So you just write the program, and you invoke the interpreter on the data,
这个程序马上就开始运行了, 所以, 我们可以说
and the program immediately begins running. And so, we can say that the
解释器是在线的, 这意味着它所做的工作都是运行的一部分
interpreter is, is online, meaning it the work that it does is all part of running
你的程序, 现在编译器的结构是不同的, 我们可以画一个图
your program. Now a compiler is structured differently. So, we can draw a picture
这里, 我们用大写的C来标记, 编译器, 编译器
here. Which we'll label with a big C, for the compiler, And the compiler takes as
输入你的程序, 然后它产生一个可执行文件。
input just your program. And then it produces an executable. And this
可执行文件是另一个程序, 可能是汇编语言, 它可能是字节码。
executable is another program, might be assembly language, it might be bytecode.
它可以是任意数量的不同的实现语言, 但是现在可以
It could be in any number of different implementation languages. But now this can
在你的数据上分开运行, 这会产生输出, 对吧？
be run separately on your data. And that will produce the output. Okay? And so in
这个结构编译器是离线的, 这意味着我们对程序进行预处理
this structure the compiler is offline, Meaning that we pre-process the program
首先, 编译器本质上是一个预处理步骤
first. The compiler is essentially a pre-processing step that produces the
可执行文件, 然后我们可以在许多不同的输入上运行相同的可执行文件,
executable, and then we can run that same executable on many, many different inputs,
在许多不同的数据集上不需要重新编译或做任何其他的处理
on many different data sets without having to recompile or do any other processing of
这个项目, 我认为给大家介绍一下这个项目是很有帮助的
the program. I think it's helpful to give a little bit of history about how
编译器和解释器首先被开发, 所以故事开始于
compilers and interpreters were first developed. So the story begins in the
20世纪50年代, 特别是IBM制造的704台机器, 这是
1950s and in particular with a machine called the 704 built by IBM. Thi s was
这是他们的第一个商业上成功的机器, 尽管有一些
their first commercially successful machine, although there had been some
他们尝试过的早期机器, 但不管怎样, 有趣的是
earlier machines that they had tried out. But anyway the interesting thing about the
704好吧, 一旦顾客开始购买并使用它, 他们就会发现
704 well, once customers started buying it and using it, is that they found that the
软件成本超过了硬件成本, 而且不仅仅是一点点, 而是
software costs exceeded the hardware costs. And not just by a little bit, but
很多时候, 这很重要, 因为这些, 这些天的硬件
by a lot And, This is important because these, the hardware in these, those days
是非常昂贵的, 即使是在硬件成本最高的时候
was extremely expensive. And even then when hardware cost the most in absolute
相对的术语, 比它们所花费的要多, 软件已经是
and relative terms, more than they would ever cost again, already the software was
占主导地位的花费, 在计算机的使用上, 这导致了
the dominant expense in, in making good use out of computers. And this led a
思考如何更好地编写软件的人的数量。
number of people to think about how they could do a better job of writing software.
他们如何使编程更有成效。
How they could make programming more productive. Where the earliest efforts to
提高编程的效率称为速度编码, 是在1953年开发的
improve the productivity of programming was called speed coding, developed in 1953
John Backus, 现在, 速度编码就是我们今天所说的, 一个早期的例子
by John Backus. Now, speed coding is what we call today, an early example of an
和所有的口译员一样, 它也有一些优点和缺点。
interpreter. And like all interpreters, it had some advantages and disadvantages. The
主要的优势是, 开发程序要快得多, 所以,
primary advantage was that it was much faster, to develop the programs. So the,
从这个意义上说, 程序员的工作效率更高, 但在其中
in that sense, the programmer was much more productive, But among its
缺点, 代码编写, 速度代码程序要慢10到20倍。
disadvantages, code written, speed code programs were ten to twenty times slower.
然后是手写的程序这也适用于今天的解释程序, 如果
Then handwritten programs and that's also true of interpreted programs today. So if
你有一个使用解释器的实现, 它们将会非常多
you have an implementation that uses an interpreter, they're going to be much
比编译器或手工编写代码要慢, 而且速度代码
slower than either a compiler or writing code by hand. And also, the speed code
解释器占用了300字节的内存, 这看起来不太像。
interpreter took up, 300 bytes of memory. And that doesn't seem like very much. In
事实上, 300字节, 今天看起来是一个非常小的程序, 但是在那些
fact, 300 bytes, today, would seem like an incredibly tiny, program. But in those
天, 你必须记住, 这是30%的记忆
days, you have to keep in mind, that this was 30 Percent Of the memory on the
机器, 这是704的全部记忆的30%
machine. So this was 30 percent of the entire memory of the 704. And so the
解释器占用的空间数量本身就是一个问题, 现在是速度编码
amount of space that the interpreter took up was itself a concern. Now speed coding
没有受到欢迎, 但是John Backus认为这是有希望的并且给了他
did not become popular, but John Backus thought it was promising and it gave him
关于另一个项目的想法, 当时最重要的应用是
the idea for another project. The most important applications in those days were
科学计算, 程序员想到的是写下公式
scientific computations, and programmers thought in terms of writing down formulas
这是机器可以执行的一种形式, 约翰认为速度的问题
in a form that the machine could execute. John thought that the problem with speed
编码是这些公式实际上是被解释的他想, 如果
coding was that the formulas were in fact interpreted and he thought if first the
公式被翻译成机器可以直接执行的形式。
formulas were translated in to a form that the machine could execute directly. That
代码会更快, 同时仍然允许程序员编写,
the code would be faster, And while still allowing the programmer to write the, the,
这些程序在高水平上, 因此是公式翻译项目或FORTRAN语言
the programs at a high level, and thus was the Formula Translation Project or FORTRAN
从1954年到1957年, FORTRAN从1954年开始运行, 有趣的是, 他们认为
Project born. Now FORTRAN ran from 1954 To 1957, And interestingly, they thought it
只需要一年的时间来编译编译器, 但最终会得到3个编译器。
would only take them one year to build the compiler but it would end up taking three.
就像今天, 他们不太擅长预测软件项目的时间
So just like today, they weren't very good at predicting how long software projects
这是一个非常成功的项目, 到1958年, 超过50%
would take. But it was a very successful project. By 1958, over 50 percent of all
代码是用FORTRAN编写的, 所以50%的程序都是用FORTRAN编写的, 那就是
code was written in FORTRAN. So 50 percent of programs were in FORTRAN, And, that is
快速采用一种新技术, 我们会很高兴的
very rapid adoption of a new technology. We would be happy with that kind of
今天的成功, 当然在那个时候他们欣喜若狂, 每个人都想
success today, and of course at that time they were ecstatic, And everybody thought
这个FORTRAN既提高了抽象层次, 也提高了程序员的水平
that FORTRAN both raised the level of abstraction, improved programmer
生产力, 让每个人都能更好地利用这些机器。
productivity, and allowed everyone to make much better use of these machines. So
FORTRAN语言是第一个成功的高级语言它对它产生了巨大的影响
FORTRAN one was the first successful high level language and it had a huge impact on
特别是计算机科学, 它导致了大量的理论工作。
computer science. In particular, it led to an enormous body of theoretical work. And
编程语言的一个有趣之处是
one of the interesting things about programming languages, actually, is the
理论和实践的结合因为这是不可能的
combination of theory. And practice because it's not really possible in
编程语言可以很好地完成工作而不需要有一个很好的掌握
programming languages to do a good job without having both a, a very good grasp
相当深入的理论和良好的工程技能, 所以有很多
of fairly deep theory and also good engineering skills. So there's a lot of
非常好的系统在编程语言中构建材料
very good systems building material in programming languages and typically it
涉及到一个非常微妙和富有成果的与理论的互动, 所以, 这个
involves a very subtle and fruitful interaction with theory. And so, and this
我认为, 这是最吸引人的地方是这个地区的主题
is one of the things, I think, that's most attractive about the area's the subject of
学习计算机科学, 而FORTRAN的影响不仅仅是在计算机上
studying computer science. And the impact of FORTRAN was not just on computer
当然, 科学研究也在开发, 实用的编译器。
science research, of course, but also on the development of, practical compilers.
事实上, 它的影响是如此深远, 以至于今天, 自动编译器仍然
And, in fact, its influence was so profound, that today, auto compilers still
保存FORTRAN语言的大纲, 那么FORTRAN语言的结构是什么？
preserve the outlines of FORTRAN one. So what was the structure of FORTRAN one?
它包含了五个阶段的词汇分析和解析, 它们一起
Well it consists five phases lexical analysis and parsing, which together take
注意语言的句法方面, 语义分析,
care of the syntactic aspects of the language, semantic analysis, which, of
当然, 要注意更多的语义方面, 比如类型和范围
course, takes care of more semantic aspects, things like types and scope
规则, 优化, 它是程序上的一个转换集合
rules. Optimization, Which is a collection of transformations on the program to
要么让它运行得更快, 要么使用更少的内存, 最后是代码生成
either make it run faster or use less memory. And finally code generation which
实际上是翻译到另一代人, 根据我们的目标,
actually does the translation to another generation. And depending on our goals,
这个翻译可能是机器码, 可能是a的咬码
that translation might be to machine codes. It might be to a bite code for a
虚拟机。它可能是另一种高级编程语言。
virtual machine. It might be to another high level programming language. Well
这就是这节课的内容, 下节课我们会讲到这些
that's it for this lecture, and next time we'll pick up here and talk about these
更详细的五个阶段。
five phases in more detail.